(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners.
Welcome back to English Pot.
My name is Marco.
- I'm Erica.
- And today we're at a party.
- Yeah, this is a great,
exciting, fun, energetic lesson.
- We're at the biggest party in the world.
Carnival in Rio.
- Okay, so Rio, this is
the name of a city, right?
- Yeah, this is a city in
Brazil called Rio de Janeiro.
- So Rio de Janeiro.
- Yeah, different pronunciation, right?
- Yeah, it sounds a lot more, I don't know.
- Authentic the mind.
- So we sometimes refer to it as Rio
just to make it shorter.
- Yeah, I think that's actually the
most common way it's referred to in Rio.
It's just like if you would say Los
Angeles, you would say LA, or yeah,
if you're talking about Kuala
Lumpur, you might say KL, same idea.
- Okay, so we have some
words that we're gonna
preview before we
listen to our dialogue.
So let's start with vocabulary preview.
- Very cabaret preview.
- Okay, vocabulary preview,
we have one word, samba drone.
- Samba drone.
- This is actually a building.
- So it's a proper now,
not a common noun, right?
- No, it's not really a common noun.
It's a proper noun, but it is a building.
- And what happens in this building?
- Basically, it's very similar to a
stadium, but each end isn't closed off.
So you have stands on one
side and stands on the other,
and you have like a
little street in the middle.
- Okay.
- So you can sit down and
you can watch people parade
or walk by and you can see
the dancers and everything.
- And so what is it used for?
- Samba drone is used
so that the samba schools
can present their
dances and their dancers
and their costumes to judges and all the
people that wanna watch them dance samba.
- Okay, so you've been
using this word samba.
- Samba.
- What is this?
- Samba is a type of dance
that Brazil is famous for.
Okay.
It's very fast dance, a
lot of hit movement,
a lot of, it's very fast,
but it's very, very nice.
And the music is based
with many different type
of tropical instruments,
so it's really, really fun.
- Can you samba?
- I can samba a little
bit, it's kinda hard.
It's trickier than what it seems.
- Okay, well, we're actually gonna hear
some samba music in the dialogue, right?
- Exactly, we're gonna hear some samba
that is actually used during carnival, so.
- Okay, so let's go to Rio
now and listen to some samba.
(upbeat music)
- I can't believe we're
here, kind of a win-real.
- Seriously, this is like a
once in a lifetime opportunity.
Can we believe it?
We're here at the
biggest party in the world.
- I know, we're still lucky we
found tickets for the samba drum.
Good thing we found that ticket scalper.
Look, it's starting.
Wow, this is amazing.
Look at how many dancers there are.
Oh my gosh, the costumes are so colorful.
This is so cool.
- It says here that the
school that is dancing now
is one of the oldest and most
prestigious samba schools in Rio.
- No kidding, look at
them, they're amazing.
Look at that girl on top of that float.
She must be the carnival queen.
We're over there, so I
can get a picture of you.
- Okay, hurry up, take the picture.
- Oh, they look like a Jain too.
- Oh, really?
No, I can't.
Really, I don't know how to dance.
(laughs)
Honey, I'll see you later.
- Patrick, don't just leave me here.
(cheering)
(upbeat music)
- All right, what a lucky
guy he got asked out
to dance by a beautiful
Brazilian samba dancer.
- I know, I don't think his
wife was very happy though.
- Well, we've got some language
about carnival in Rio, right?
- Exactly.
- So let's look at that now
with language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, our first word on
language takeaway today, ticket scalper.
- Ticket scalper.
- This is actually a job title, I think.
(laughs)
- Maybe not a totally legal job title.
- Exactly.
- So what does a ticket scalper do?
- Basically, this person will sell tickets
at a higher price to people
who don't have tickets.
- Okay, so he buys like 100 tickets and
goes and stands outside of the samba drum
or the stadium and he sells
them for like twice the price, right?
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, that's a ticket scalper.
Actually, they come in handy sometimes
because you wanna go to a concert or something
and you don't have tickets,
you gotta turn to them, right?
- Right?
- Okay, our next word, prestigious.
- prestigious.
- This is a very nice word, prestigious.
- Mm-hmm.
- Before we explain anything,
let's listen to some examples.
- Example one.
- Harvard University is one of the most
prestigious schools in North America.
- Example two.
The Academy Award
is the most prestigious
prize an actor can
get in the film industry.
- Example three.
- He worked really hard and now
he's a very prestigious heart surgeon.
- I can see that when something is
prestigious, it's really well-respected, right?
- It's well-known, well-respected.
- And if you are part of this
thing, you can feel a sense of pride.
- Right, prestige.
- Okay, now let's take a
look at our last word, float.
- Float.
- Now this doesn't mean
to float in water, right?
- No, this is a now, not a verb.
It's kinda hard to describe, actually.
- Yeah, it is hard to describe.
A float is something that
you commonly see in parades.
- Right, so it would be like a
car, but you can't really see the car.
- No, 'cause it's covered with decorations.
- With big decorations and it's
made to look like an artificial island.
- Yeah, or a tree, maybe.
- So you have people standing
on there and dancing or waving.
- Yeah.
- Okay, we'll definitely
post a picture of a float
on our comments section so
you can see what a float looks like.
- Right.
- Okay, so now let's listen
to our dialogue again.
We're gonna slow it down a little bit
so you can understand all of these words.
We've just talked about.
(upbeat music)
- I can't believe we're here.
Carnival in Rio, seriously.
This is like a once in
a lifetime opportunity.
Can you believe it?
We're here at the
biggest party in the world.
- I know, we're so lucky that we
found tickets for the samba drum.
Good thing we found that ticket scalper.
- Look, it's starting.
Wow, this is amazing.
Look at how many dancers there are.
Oh my gosh, the costumes are so colorful.
This is so cool.
- It says here that the
school that is dancing now
is one of the oldest and most
prestigious samba schools in Rio.
- No kidding, look at them.
They're amazing.
Look at that girl on top of that float.
She must be the carnival queen.
Move over there so I
can get a picture of you.
- Okay, hurry up, take the picture.
Oh, really?
No, I can't, no.
Really, I don't know how to dance.
How do you, I'll see you later.
- Patrick, don't just leave me here.
(upbeat music)
All right, we're back.
So now I think we should take
a look at some of the phrases.
- Yeah, let's go to fluency builder.
- All right.
Fluency builder.
- So we have this
phrase once in a lifetime.
- Once in a lifetime.
- So this is an expression you would use
to say that it doesn't happen very often.
- Yeah, it's a really special event.
- So like a once in a lifetime opportunity.
- Or a once in a lifetime chance.
- Okay, yeah, once in a lifetime.
Let's look at our next phrase.
Good thing.
- Good thing.
- So we have some examples for good thing.
Why don't we listen to them
and then we'll come back.
- Example one.
- Good thing I studied for my exam.
It was really hard.
- Example two.
- It's a good thing I brought my umbrella.
It rained the whole day.
- Example three.
- It's a good thing that I bought in
my house before the prices went up.
- Good thing I had money in my wallet.
- You're happy you had
money in your wallet.
- If you could also maybe
use it as a negative, right?
Like, good thing I didn't go.
- Right, I'm happy I didn't
go because it was terrible.
- Okay, good thing.
- Yep.
- All right, now let's take
a look at our last word.
No kidding.
- No kidding.
- Okay, so many of you probably
already know this word, kidding, right?
- Yeah, it means joking.
- Yeah, I'm joking, just kidding.
- Yeah.
- Okay, but if I would say no kidding,
you're saying like, yeah,
I totally agree with you.
- Right, I agree with you.
I know you are.
- I know you're being serious.
- Yeah, I know it's true.
- Yeah.
- So I could say, wow, this
restaurant is really expensive.
- No kidding.
- Yeah, so you would
agree, it's like, yeah, for real.
- Yeah.
- All right.
- So this term, no
kidding, is slang, right?
- It's a little bit informal, yeah.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Okay.
So why don't we listen
to our dialogue again
for the third time and then we'll
come back and talk about Brazil.
(upbeat music)
- I can't believe we're here.
Kind of a little seriously.
This is like a once in
a lifetime opportunity.
Can we believe it?
We're here at the
biggest party in the world.
- I know, we're still looking.
We found tickets for the samba drum.
Good thing we found that ticket scalper.
- Look, it's starting.
Wow, this is amazing.
Look at how many dancers there are.
Oh my gosh, the costumes are so colorful.
This is so cool.
It says here that the
school that is dancing now
is one of the oldest and most
prestigious samba schools in Rio.
- No kidding, look at them.
They're amazing.
Look at that girl on top of that float.
She must be the carnival queen.
We're over there, so I
can get a picture of them.
- Okay, hurry up, take the picture.
- Oh, they look like a jang ching.
- Oh, really?
No, I can't.
No, I clearly, I don't know how to dance.
Honey, I'll see you later.
- Gotcha, don't just leave me here.
- Woo!
- All right, Marco, so carnival.
It's a Brazilian celebration, right?
- It's very popular in all Latin America.
- Oh, really?
- Yeah, but Brazilian
carnival is very, very special.
- Okay, so what are they celebrating?
- So basically, it's the beginning of Lent,
which is this period of
time in the Catholic religion
right before Easter, but carnival
in Brazil is very special because
of all the dancing in all of this
and costumes and everything.
- Yeah, well, from the dialogue,
it sounds really wild and
crazy, so what happens?
- Well, it definitely is really amazing,
and it's just basically a lot
of samba music and partying,
and it's really nice, and especially
to be able to see something
so spectacular, it's like hundreds
and thousands of dancers
in the samba drum, and
they're parading down in their
costumes and in floats, so
it's a very, very special event.
- All right, so it
sounds like a lot of fun.
- Yeah.
- I want to hear from our listeners.
- Yeah, for sure, we
have a lot of listeners from
Brazil, and carnival is
not only celebrated in Rio,
it's also in Sao Paulo,
in Pernambuco, in Bahia,
and it's a little bit different
in each place, so it's
not just a thing of Rio,
it's just more popular there.
- Is there a samba drone in each city?
- Yeah, there is a samba
drone in Sao Paulo, yeah.
- Oh, cool.
- Yeah, let us know if
you've ever been to carnival,
or how you celebrate it in
your hometown or in your city.
- Yeah, come to our
website, Englishpod.
com, and leave us your
comments all about carnival.
- Exactly, and everyone, be
sure to come, because we're
gonna post some videos of what
samba is like and some photos,
so you can get an idea of this
really interesting Brazilian celebration.
- Okay, everyone, thanks for
listening, and until next time, goodbye.
(upbeat music)